Guide to the Cornelius Rea Agnew Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Cornelius Rea Agnew Papers,
1851-1924
Agnew, Cornelius Rea, 1830-1888.
6 linear ft (ca. 6,000 items in 13 boxes and 2 flats).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, New York 10027.
4078774
Biographical Note
Professor of diseases of the eye and ear at the College of Physicians and Surgeons. Agnew, a prominent New York ophthalmologist, also helped organize the eye and ear hospital in Manhattan. (Columbia B.A., 1849; M.D., 1852)
Scope and Content
Correspondence, notes, and manuscripts including items that relate to most of Agnew's professional activities, are especially rich in materials that deal with the treatment of eye diseases during the latter half of the 19th century. An interesting sidelight of the collection is a group of finely detailed woodblocks and steel plates that Agnew used to illustrate his published articles.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Seties II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts, Lectures & Speeches
Series IV: Subject Files
Series V: Patients' Records
Series VI: Diaries, Journals & Photographs
Series VII: Awards & Degrees
Series VIII: Memorabilia
Series IX: Printed
Subjects
Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889.; Burgess, John William, 1844-1931.; Egleston, Thomas, 1832-1900.; Strong, George Templeton, 1820-1875.; Eye--Diseases.; Ophthalmology--Study and teaching.; Ophthalmology--Research.; Hospitals--New York (State)--New York.; Diaries.; Engravings.; Journals.; Photographs.; Printing plates.; Scrapbooks.; Woodblocks.; Educators.; Ophthalmologists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1972 M72-9-7 Spahn, Mrs. Donald, via Medical Library Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Agnew, Cornelius Rea To [v.p.], [v.p.], [n.d.] & 1851-1887, (54 Folders) (Box 1)
  - Astor, Caroline Webster Schermerhorn To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York [n.y.], (2 p. a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1878-1887, (12 a.l.s 13 ms.l 1 a.l.) (Box 1)
  - Barnard, Margaret McMurray (Mrs. Frederick) To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York [n.d.], (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Burgess, John William To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 15 March [n.y.], (1 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Chandler, Charles Frederick To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1865-1879, (4 a.l.s 2 ms.l.) (Box 1)
  - Cornell, Alonzo B. To: Cornelius Rea Agnew [n.p.] 30 November 1880, (1 p. a.d.s. election certificate) (Box 1)
  - Dix, Dorthea Lynde To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Trenton, N.J. 23 July, 1870, (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Dix, Morgan To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1 January, 1880, (1 p. a.l. [in third person]) (Box 1)
  - Egleston, Thomas To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1878-1880, (4 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Eliot, Ellsworth To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1869-1882, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Evarts, William Maxwell To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Washington 4 January, 1880, (1 p. a.l. [in third person]) (Box 1)
  - Freemont, Jessie Benton To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Pocaho, New York [and n.p.] [n.d.], (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gerry, Elbridge Thomas To: W.H. Katzenbach New York 2 July 1885, (1 p. t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gerry, Elbridge Thomas To: David Webster New York 26 December 1885, (1 p. a.l.s. [with envelope]) (Box 1)
  - Gilman, Daniel Coit To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Yosemite, California 12 July, 1889, (3 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gould, Benjamin Apthorp To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Cambridge, Mass. 27 May, 1865 and 8 January 1866 2 a.l.s. (Box 1)
  - Hewitt, Abram Stevens To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1869-1872, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Lossing, Benson John To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Dover Plains, New York 1881-1883, (4 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Low, Abiel Abbott To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 5 January, 1880, (4 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Marble, Manton To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 2 April 1869, (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Philadelphia 4 February, 1870, (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Morgan, Edwin Denison To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Washington 18 and 22 December, 1869, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Morton, Levi Parsons To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 2 January 1880, (1 p. a.l. [in third person]) (Box 1)
  - Mott, Valentine To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York [n.d.], (1 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, James To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Hyde Park, New York 15 October 1873 and 14 may 1874, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 16 and 17 June 1865, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Schermerhorn, Frederick Augustus To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 17 June 1864 and 3 April 1883, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Schuyler To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York and Albany, New York 1880-1881, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Strong, George Templeton To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 1865-1873 and [n.d.], (7 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Toynbee, Joseph To: Cornelius Rea Agnew London 26 June, 1856 and 23 June 1860, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Tweed, William Marcy To: Cornelius Rea Agnew Albany, New York 24 March 1869 and 9 April 1869, (21 a.l.s 1 telegram) (Box 1)
  - Van Amringe, John Howard To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 2 January 1879, (1 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Van Amringe, John Howard To: Cornelius Rea Agnew New York 2 January 1879, (1 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1)
- Seties II: Arranged Correspondence
  - [v.p.] To: C.R. Agnew [n.d.] & 1856-1864 (Box 2)
  - [v.p.] To: C.R. Agnew 1867-1875 (Box 3)
  - [v.p.] To: C.R. Agnew 1876-1888 Correspondence (Box 4)
- Series III: Manuscripts, Lectures & Speeches
  - Manuscripts, published articles, bibliography (Box 5)
  - Lectures and speeches (Box 6)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - Amtab Medical College (Turkey) (Box 7)
  - Hoffmann Island (Box 7)
  - Loring Affair (Box 7)
  - Manhattan Eye and Ear Hospital (Box 7)
  - Medical Missionary Society (Box 7)
  - Randall's Island (Box 7)
  - State Charities and Associations (Box 7)
  - Two Articles by David Webster, M.D. (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 8)
  - Minutes and Notes of Misc. Meetings (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Unidentified Notes (Box 8)
- Series V: Patients' Records
  - Patient Records and Medical Histories (Box 9)
- Series VI: Diaries, Journals & Photographs
  - Diaries, Journals, Photos and Engravings (Box 10)
- Series VII: Awards & Degrees
  - Degrees, Honorary Degrees, Awards, Invitations, Licenses (Box 11)
- Series VIII: Memorabilia
  - Carved Woodblocks and Engraved Steel plates (Box 12)
- Series IX: Printed
  - Printed Materials (Box 13 & 14)